ATHM Textile Industry Stereographs 6524/006 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series II: General Images Organized by Textile Related Subject
  - Bleaching (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Item 1: Bleachery, Willimantic Linen Co.'s Thread Works, Willimantic Conn. (Box 11, Folder 5)
      Hartford, Conn.: Prescott & White, Photographers, ca. 1880s. Gelatin silver print. Black and white image shows the bleachery in the Willimantic Linen Co. Fabric is piled up on the right between large vats; what may be yarn or thread is piled up on the left. A male employee in the background stirs one of the vats; two other men are on the right. 17.25 x 8.25 cm.
    - Item 2: Bleaching Linen, Near Belfast, Ireland (Box 11, Folder 5)
      Black and white image of of men either loading linen onto a horse-drawn cart or unloading it. Linen can be bleached after being woven by having it spread out in the fields to be bleached by the sun and dew, as can be seen in the background here. [Meadville, Pa.]: Keystone View Company, ca. 1900-1920. 18 x 9 cm.
  - Engraving and Printing (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Item 1: Attrezzi per l'incisione dell Planches da stampa. [Tools for engraving of Planches] (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Item 2: Dipinto rafffigurante stampatori al lavoro (A. Colombo). [Painted rafffigurante printers at work] (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Item 3: Copying design on copper rolls for printing cotton cloth, Lawrence, Mass. (Box 11, Folder 6)
      Keystone View Company. Copying design on copper rolls for printing cotton cloth, Lawrence, Mass. Gelatin silver print, copyrighted by The Keystone View Company. Black-and-white image depicts a woman sitting at a table, painting the design onto an engraved zinc plate. Another woman, mostly unseen, stands to the left holding a large design. The mill in which this takes place is not identified but is most likely the Pacific Mills in Lawrence, Mass. Text on reverse: "Copying Design to be Printed on Cotton Cloth, Lawrence, Mass. [explanation of weaving and singing cloth]. This cloth is now ready for market as white cloth. But much of the demand is for colored or patterned goods. The patterns are printed on the white cloth by copper rolls, much after the fashion of paper printing on roller presses. To get the design on the rolls is the next step. This is the making and the transferring of the design. Skilled artists draft suitable designs. These are photographed, engraved on zinc, and transferred to the copper rollers by a chemical process. Each color demands a separate plate. The girl in the view is busy painting on the engraved zinc plate, those parts of the pattern which belong to one color. Making ready the copper rolls for printing is one of the most interesting processes of cloth manufacture." ca. 1914. 17.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 4: Printing Room, Cotton Mills, Orizaba, Mexico., 1904 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      Black and white image of a printing room in a cotton mill in Orizaba, Mexico. A row of printing machines lines the wall to the left. A printing machine can print up to 14 colors. Cotton is by far the most common fabric to be printed. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company. 17.5 x 9 cm.
    - Item 5: Printing color designs on silk cloth, 10 colors at once, in a great silk dyeing works, N.J. (Box 11, Folder 6)
      Printing color designs on silk cloth, 10 colors at once, in a great silk dyeing works, N.J. Black and white image of men printing color designs on silk cloth. Each roller that is seen in the foreground prints a different color and the pattern must match exactly. The man in the foreground is the expert printer, who will make adjustments as needed to make sure the pattern is printed perfectly. No mill is given, but this is possibly Paterson, N.J., which was a center of the silk industry in the U.S. New York: Underwood & Underwood, ca. 1900-1920. 17.5 x 9 cm.
    - Item 6: General View in Large Printing Room of Cotton Mills, Lawrence, Mass. (Box 11, Folder 6)
      General View in Large Printing Room of Cotton Mills, Lawrence, Mass. Black and white image of a massive printing room in Lawrence, Mass. "The view shows the enormous extent of one of these printing rooms. You will observe the printed cloth coming over. A foreman is here seen inspecting a bit of print." Although not specifically identified, this is the Pacific Mills in Lawrence. The print works finished about 5,000,000 yards of cloth each week at this time. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company, ca. 1913-1920. This image appears on page 221 of the March 1920 issue of The National Geographic Magazine. 17.5 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 7: Printing Cloth--Silk Industry, So. Manchester, Conn., 1914 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      Black-and-white image shows large printing cylinder used to print silk cloth. Up to twelve rollers may be used to print a design directly on the silk cloth, rather than have it woven into the cloth. Although not specificed, this is the Cheney Bros. plant in South Manchester, Conn. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company. 17.75 x 9 cm.
    - Item 8: Cotton print stampers (Box 11, Folder 6)
      Black and white image of two Indian men in traditional dress, kneeling in front of a low table on which is spread a printed fabric, using hand blocks to stamp the fabric. Universal Postal Union, British India. ca. 1900-1905. 13. 5 x 9 cm.
    - Item 9: Setting the Rug Patterns (Box 11, Folder 6)
      Black and white image of women working setting rug patterns in an unknown carpet mill. The tables at which the women work are loaded with spindles of yarn. Addressed to someone in Bloomsburg, Pa.; may possibly be the Magee Carpet Co. in Bloomsburg. Written on reverse: "Aunt Lydia worked here." ca. 1905-1907. 14 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 10: Printing Room, American Print Works, Fall River, Mass. (Box 11, Folder 6)
      Littleton, New Hampshire: Photographed and published by Kilburn Bros., ca. 1875-1885. Gelatin silver print. Black and white image depicts male workers standing by the printing machines in a long row of machines. These machines printed patterns onto fabric. 17 x 8.25 cm.
    - Item 11: Pentagraph [Pantograph] Room, American Print Works, Fall River, Mass. (Box 11, Folder 6)
      Littleton, New Hampshire: Photographed and published by Kilburn Brothers, ca. 1880-1888. Gelatin silver print. Black and white image shows a female worker seated at an open table on which is a pantograph. A pantograph [from Wikipedia] "is a mechanical linkage connected in a manner based on parallelograms so that the movement of one pen, in tracing an image, produces identical movements in a second pen." This is most likely being used to design prints for fabrics. Another woman stands behind the pantograph machine. 17 x 8.25 cm.
  - Inspection and Repairing (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Item 1: Inspecting and perfecting the finished fabrics--Brainerd & Armstrong's weaving department (Box 11, Folder 7)
      Color image shows women sitting in chairs at drafting tables with colored cloth on the slanted surface in front of them that they are inspecting for flaws. The walls are brick and each woman has a pendant light fixture hanging above her head. One woman is standing and appears to be inspecting a plaid fabric. Brainerd & Armstrong was located in New London, Conn. Chilton Printing Co., Philadelphia, Pa. ca. 1907-1915. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 2: Inspecting Combed Silk- Silk Industry (Spun Silk), So. Manchester, Conn., U.S.A., 1914 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      Black-and-white image shows a woman inspecting combed silk. After the combed silk is taken from the dressing machine it is carefully inspected and the remaining impurities are removed by hand. The work is done in a dark room upon a plate of glass lighted from below. The inspector spreads out the combed silk on this glass and any dirt, or other impurity not removed by the dressing machine, becomes plainly visible. Piles of combed silk are shown here on the glass table on either side of the inspector, as well as larger piles on the shelf above. Although not specified, this is the Cheney Brothers plant in South Manchester. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 3: Testing Cord Fabric for Automobile Tires, Akron, Ohio (Box 11, Folder 7)
      Black and white image of a man examining cord fabric for automobile tires. Heavy threads from long-staple cotton are woven into wide sheets of cord fabric; the workman in this image is inspecting the cotton fabric while it is passing over a glass table that has strong lights underneath it. He is examining the material through a magnifiying glass to make sure it is perfect. A sheet of this cotton will eventually be run between heavy rollers and the rubber is pressed in between the threads of the cloth so they are like one piece of material. Many layers of such material are used in a tire. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company, ca. 1900-1920. 17.5 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 4: Inspecting the Finished Fabric in the Shipping Department--Linen Industry, Canada, 1908 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      Black and white image shows a man inspecting some finished fabric spread out on a table. The fabric is closely examined for any flaws or faults. No specific mill is cited, other than in Canada. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company. 18 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 5: Cloth Inspection Dept., Bemis Bro. Bag Co. (Box 11, Folder 7)
      Sepia image of a mill room with three male workers, two of whom are inspecting cloth and one, wearing a hat on the left, who may be an overseer or supervisor. Made by the Artvue Post Card Co., 225 Fifth Ave., New York, N.Y. ca. 1930s. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 6: Gray cloth examination, Pacific Mills, Lawrence, Mass. (Box 11, Folder 7)
      Gelatin silver print. Black and white image of a woman inspecting gray cloth at the Pacific Mills, Lawrence, Mass. The cloth is rolled out from the top so that it can be closely examined for flaws, etc. "Gray cloth" does not mean cloth that is gray in color but simply material that has not been bleached in any way. ca. 1900-1920. 17.5 x 9 cm.
    - Item 7: Burling Room, Washington Mills Interior, Lawrence, Mass. (Box 11, Folder 7)
      ca. 1880. Published by A. B. Hamor. Burling is a finishing process usually used on woolens and worsteds, by which knots, loose threads, etc. are removed by hand. Note the piles of fabric on the right. 17.5 x 10 cm.
  - Fulling and Washing (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Item 1: A tour through Messrs Lupton and Co's Woollen Mills, Leeds. 1773-1958:fulling (Box 11, Folder 8)
      Black and white image depicts a man working at the fulling stocks in Lupton & Co.'s woolen mill in Leeds, England. Printed on reverse: "The lengths of loosely woven woollen cloth were soaked in a special solution and pounded under huge hammers called 'fulling stocks.' This fulling, as it was known, caused the cloth to shrink by almost a third, and as a result, it became much thicker and more weatherproof." Number seven in a series of eight. Postcard by Armley Mills, Leeds Museum of Science and Industry. Printed by E. T. W. Dennis & Sons Ltd., Scarborough, England. This postcard was printed in 1982 as the Leeds Museum of Science and Industry was created in 1982, but the image probably dates from an earlier period. ca. 1982. 15 x 10 cm.
    - Item 2: "Weighting" and washing silk skeins, before dyeing, in Paterson Factory, N.J. (Box 11, Folder 8)
      Black and white image of men working in a Paterson, N.J., silk mill. Weighting consists of immersing the silk in a tin solution to increase its weight and give it body. The round vats seen here contain the tin in solution. The silk is put in these vats and while rotating rapidly, absorbs the solution of tin. The silk after weighting is ready to go into the dyeing room. New York: Underwood & Underwood, ca. 1900-1920. 17.5 x 9 cm.
    - Item 3: Wet process finishing (Box 11, Folder 8)
      Black and white image of the interior of an unknown mill, showing the area where the wet finishing would take place. Wet finishing is a general term for those finishing processes in which the material is immersed in, or becomes wet with, water. ca. 1910-1917. 8.5 x 13.5 cm.
  - Dyeing (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Item 1: Two rows of vats (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Item 2: Barca ad aspo per tintura [Boat reel for dyeing] (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Item 3: Laboratororio chimico [Chemical laboratory] (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Item 4: Bilance [The balance] (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Item 5: Small Section of the Brainerd & Armstrong Dyeing Plant [New London, Conn.] (Box 11, Folder 9)
      Color image shows men standing next to racks with fabric hung over rods. The building has brick walls and the ceiling is open. One man is standing in the sill of a window in the left background. The reverse of the postcard is a form letter indicating that a salesman will be calling on the recipient. Made by Chilton Printing Co., Phila., Pa., U.S.A. ca. 1907-1915. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 6: A tour through Messrs Lupton and Co's Woolen Mills, Leeds, 1773-1958: dyeing (Box 11, Folder 9)
      Black-and-white image depicts vats in the wool dyehouse, where wool would be dyed once it had been scoured and cleaned. Number two in a series of eight. Postcard by Armley Mills, Leeds Museum of Science and Industry. Printed by E. T. W. Dennis & Sons Ltd., Scarborough, England. This postcard was printed in 1982 as the Leeds Museum of Science and Industry was created in 1982, but the image probably dates from an earlier period. ca. 1982. 15 x 11 cm.
    - Item 7: Dyeing Machine, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      Color image of a man standing next to a large dyeing machine, which is nearly twice as tall as he is. Printed on reverse: "Another unit in the famous line of high-quality Rodney Hunt wet finishing equipment ready for shipment to a satisfed customer! Type P Model '85' stainless steel Tru- Shade Dyeing Machine." Orange, Mass.: Rodney Hunt Machine Co., Textile Machinery Division. Postmarked January 12, 1962 in Orange. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 8: Dyeing silk in the piece in a mammoth silk dyeing works, Paterson N.J. (Box 11, Folder 9)
      Black and white image of men working in a the piece dyeing plant of the National Silk and Dyeing Co. in Paterson, N.J. New York: Underwood & Underwood, ca. 1900-1920. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 9: Vats for dyeing Cloth in the Piece- Silk Industry, So. Manchester, Conn., U.S.A., 1914 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      Black and white image of vats for dyeing cloth in the piece- dyeing room of the Cheney Bros. factory. The vats are filled with dyes and the cloth is run through them over the reel in the center. The cloth is then compared with the sample and if the color is not right, colors are added to the dye until the right shade is reached. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 10: Bleaching Vats for Cloth in the Piece-Silk Industry, So. Manchester, Conn., U.S.A., 1914 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      Black and white image of bleaching vats for cloth in the piece. The vat is filled with the bleaching liquor and the cloth run back and forth through it over the reel in the center. One male employee is visible in the right background. Although not specified, this is the Cheney Bros. plant in South Manchester, Conn. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 11: Dyehouse with Hydro-extractor: Extractors (left center), Dye Becks (both sides) (Box 11, Folder 9)
      Dye Becks (both sides). Black-and-white image of unknown dyehouse, showing hydro-extrators in the left center. A hydro-extractor is a machine for expeling the loose water from raw stock, yarn, cloth, etc., by means of centrifugal force. The wet material is loaded in a perforated cage or basket that can be rapidly rotated, thus slinging out the water. Dye becks are machines for dyeing piece goods. Four male laborers stand in the background. Handwritten message on reverse of card is dated Dec. 10, 1907, Lowell, Mass., but it is unclear if this dyehouse is located in Lowell. ca. 1907. 13.5 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 12: "Stripping" and color dyeing skeins, in an immense silk dyeing works, Paterson, N.J. (Box 11, Folder 9)
      Black and white image of men working in a plant of the National Silk & Dyeing Company in Paterson, N.J. Stripping is the boiling off of the superfluous gums and oils that would interfere with the dyeing. This process is going on in the first tier of tubs on the right. After stripping and weighting, the silk is returned to this room to be dyed in the tanks beyond the tub in the foreground. The skeins are suspended from wooden rods across the tubs full of hot dye-liquor. The skeins are moved and turned frequently for several hours until the right shade is obtained. New York: Underwood & Underwood, ca. 1900-1920. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 13: Livre de teinturier, avec echantillons et recettes, XVIIIe - XIXe s. [Book of dyers with samples and recipes] (Box 11, Folder 9)
      Musee de la View Wallonne. Liege, Belgium.
  - Raising (Napping) (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Item 1: Raising frame or "nelly" (Box 11, Folder 10)
      Tolson Memorial Museum, Huddersfield, England. [no later than 1962] Black and white image shows a raising frame, used to raise the nap on fabric. 9 x 14 cm.
  - Shearing and Singeing (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Item 1: Hand cropping shears and board (Box 11, Folder 11)
      Tolson Memorial Museum, Huddersfield, England. [no later than 1962] Black and white image shows a set of hand cropping shears, in this case used to shear the nap of fabric, laid on a board. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 2: Lewis cross-cut machine (shearing) (Box 11, Folder 11)
      Tolson Memorial Museum, Huddersfield, England. [no later than 1962] Black and white image shows a Lewis cross-cut machine used for shearing the nap of fabric. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 3: "Perpetual" or "Jerry" shearing machine (Box 11, Folder 11)
      Tolson Memorial Museum, Huddersfield, England. [no later than 1962] Black and white image shows a shearing machine used for shearing the nap of fabric. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 4: Shearing the nap on woolen fabrics in a big modern mill (Box 11, Folder 11)
      Black and white image of a man working at a shearing machine. A shearing machine shears cloth by mechanically trimming the projecting fibers from the surface of a cloth. The cutting action is provided by means of a roller on which are spirally mounted a number of steel blades. This rotates in close contact with a fixed ledger blade, the cloth passing between the two. The location of this mill is unknown. New York: Underwood & Underwood, ca. 1900-1920. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 5: Cropping the finished Fabric (Box 11, Folder 11)
      Black and white image shows men working in a room filled with shearing machines. A shearing machine shears cloth by mechanically trimming the projecting fibers from the surface of a cloth. The cutting action is provided by means of a roller on which are spirally mounted a number of steel blades. This rotates in close contact with a fixed ledger blade, the cloth passing between the two. The location of this mill is unknown. Carter's Series No. 58. Printed in Britain. [no earlier than 1902] 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 6: Cropping shop, late 18th C. (Box 11, Folder 11)
      Black-and-white image depicts a late 18th-century cropping shop, where the surface of fabric is sheared by hand. Shearing is a finishing operation where the projecting fibers from the surface of a cloth are cut or trimmed. Here a man uses an implement to shear the cloth. Note the large pair of shears on the wall on the left. [Published by] Textile Department, Bankfield Museum, Halifax [Yorkshire, England]. Formerly a private residence, Bankfield was sold in 1887 and was transformed into a museum. ca. 1930-1960. 14 x 8.75 cm.
  - Calendering (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Item 1: Making carriage cloth with great Calender machine. (Box 11, Folder 12)
      Black and white image shows male workers operating calender machine in unknown textile mill. Note the large roll of fabric on the left. New York: Underwood & Underwood, ca. 1900-1920. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 2: Calendering and Rolling. (Box 11, Folder 12)
      Black and white image shows calendering machine in operation in an unknown textile mill. Carter's Series No. 59. Printed in Britain. [no earlier than 1902] 13.75 x 9 cm.
    - Item 3: Putting the Rough Linen Fabric through the Cropping MachineLinen Industry, Canada (Box 11, Folder 12)
      Black and white image shows a boy operating a cropping machine in an unknown Canadian textile mill. A cropping machine (the cropper) is one of three machines used in the overall calendering (dressing) process; the other two being the mangler and the calender. While the mangler and the calender are massive in size, the cropper is relatively small and easily operated by a young boy. A cropper is used to bring forth a fabric's smooth and lustrous appearance. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company, ca. 1900-1920. 17.75 x 9 cm.
    - Item 4: Huge Rollers at Work, Linen Factory, Belfast, Ireland. (Box 11, Folder 12)
      Black and white image of a man, in an unkown Irish linen factory, working at a calendering machine. The male operative wears a long white apron over his clothes. Calendering is one of the finishing processes for fabric. Note the piles of fabric in the left foreground. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company, ca. 1900-1920. 17.75 x 9 cm.
  - Winding, Folding, and Pressing (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Item 1: In the folding and making up room, rolls of finished silk, Paterson Silk Works [Paterson, N.J.] (Box 11, Folder 13)
      In the folding and making up room, rolls of finished silk, Paterson Silk Works [Paterson, N.J.]. Black and white image of many workersmostly femalepreparing silk goods for the market by folding and boxing them. "Paterson Silk Works" may refer to the Paterson Broad Silk Works, which was out of business by 1905, or it may refer to the silk mills in Paterson in general. New York: Underwood & Underwood, ca. 1900-1910. 17.75 x 9 cm.
    - Item 2: A tour through Messrs Lupton and Co's Woollen Mills, Leeds. 1773-1958: folding (Box 11, Folder 13)
      Black-and-white image shows a horse attached to a cloth-carrying cart, as a man stands by the horse's head. Behind the horse and man is a brick mill building. Printed on reverse: "Having been fulled and if necessary piece dyed, at the company's Cliffe Mills, Pudsey, the cloth was loaded onto horse-drawn wagons to be transported to their Whitehall Mills, Leeds, for finishing." Number eight in a series of eight by Armley Mills, Leeds Museum of Science and Industry. Printed by E.T.W. Dennis & Sons, Ltd., Scarborough. This postcard was printed in 1982, as that is when the Leeds Museum of Science and Industry was created, but the image dates from an earlier period. ca. 1982. 15 x 10.5 cm.
    - Item 3: Folding Room, American Print Works, Fall River, Mass. (Box 11, Folder 13)
      Littleton, New Hampshire: Photographed and published by Kilburn Bros., ca. 1875-1885. Gelatin silver print. Black and white image depicts male and female workers in the folding room of the American Print Works. Finished material was folded during this process. 17 x 8.25 cm.
    - Item 4: Cloth Market in the Great Fair of Nijni-Novgorod, Russia. (Box 11, Folder 13)
      Black and white image shows a large crowd of people at an outdoor cloth market. The "fair," which contains a variety of goods and hosts "hundreds of thousands of visitors and traders" from all over Russia, is actually a market-place that has operated during the summer "[f]or at least six centuries." The building in the background may be a permanent structure that only sees use during the market season; the location is practically deserted outside of the summer. Events such as World War I and the Russian Revolution caused a dwindling in the market's significance. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company, ca. 1920. 17.75 x 9 cm.